Inventory of the Prinzessin Stephanie Juliana zu Hohenlohe-Waldenburg-Schillingsfürst papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Prinzessin Stephanie Juliana zu Hohenlohe-Waldenburg-Schillingsfürst papers
1914-1973
1938-1972
77020
Hoover Institution Archives
7 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes (3.6 linear feet)
Correspondence, writings, memoranda, telegrams, news clippings, manuscripts, and printed matter relating to Anglo-German relations in the 1930s, political developments in Hungary, and detailing the personal and literary activities of Princess Stephanie from 1914 to 1972.
Hohenlohe-Waldenburg-Schillingsfürst, Stephanie Juliana, Prinzessin zu, 1896-1972.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1891 Born in Vienna, Austria
1914 Married Prince Friedrich Franz von Hohenlohe-Waldenburg-Schillingsfürst
1917-1918 Served as a volunteer nurse in World War I
1920 Divorced Prince Friedrich
1927 Met Harold Sidney Harmsworth, 1st Viscount Rothermere, and became his emissary and confidant
1933 Acted as an liasion between Adolf Hitler and Lord Rothermere. European Press accuse Princess Stephanie of espionage
1937 Hitler distanced himself from the Princess
1938 Emigrated to London and sued Lord Rothermere for breach of contract
1940-1941 Moved to the United States and arrested by Immigration and Naturalization Services
1959-1972 Returned to Europe and became a literary consultant for various magazine publications
1972 Died in Geneva, Switzerland
Scope and Content of Collection
The Prinzessin Stephanie Juliana zu Hohenlohe-Waldenburg-Schillingsfürst papers document her participation in foreign relations, her legal proceedings against Lord Rothermere, and literary endeavors. Princess Stephanie was recognized as an emissary and rumored to be a spy between Lord Rothermere and Adolf Hitler prior to World War II; in which the collection details through correspondence, telegrams, newspaper articles, and legal documents. The collection contains a considerable amount of materials relating Princess Stephanie’s literary years after World War II where she attempted to write and publish her autobiography as well as act as a consultant and agent with various magazine publishers and journalists, which are detailed in correspondence, articles, invoices, and manuscripts.
The Biographical File is comprised of a notebook, address book, and personal identification cards.
The Correspondence in the papers reflects the wide array of Princess Stephanie's professional relationships. Included are an exchange of letters, telegrams, and memorandums between Lord Rothermere and Adolf Hitler as well as correspondence in regards to Princess Stephanie’s litigation against Lord Rothermere, her internment in the United States, and literary career. Due in part to Hohenlohe’s close collaboration with Lord Rothermere, various journalists and publishing organizations, the collection includes articles and correspondence by others Princess Stephanie had collected. The file concludes with collected condolences received upon Princess Stephanie’s death.
The Writings contains an essay on Hungary in 1956, in regards to the Hungarian Revolution, and drafts of Princess Stephanie's unpublished memoirs.
The Subject Files predominantly focuses on Princess Stephanie’s literary career. To keep with original order, there is diversity in the forms of materials within each folders; for example, news clippings, additional correspondence, articles and invoices detailing her work and that of her associates: Drew Pearson, Jack Anderson, Ryan McHugh, and Axel Springer.
The remainder of the collection is Printed Material and Oversized Materials which consist primarily of magazine and newspaper clippings related to the case between Lord Rothermere and Princess Stephanie, public reactions to accusations of her acts of espionage, and news relating to colleagues.
Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945; Pearson, Drew, Andrew Russell Pearson, 1897-1969; Rothermere, Harold Sidney Harmsworth, 1st viscount, 1868-1940.; Springer, Axel, 1912-1985; Germany--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Germany.; Hungary--Politics and government--1918-1945.; Hungary--Politics and government--1945-1989.
- Biographical File, 1951-1962
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains personal effects like identification papers, a notebook, and an address book. Arranged by format.
  - Notebook and addressbook, undated (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Visa and identification papers, 1951-1962 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Correspondence, 1914-1973
  Contains letters,telegrams, invoices, news-clippings, invoices, and memoranda. Includes collected correspodence between Lord Rothermere and Adolf Hitler and publishers. Arranged chronologically.
  - 1914 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - 1927 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - 1928 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - 1930 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - 1932 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - 1933 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 1934 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - 1935 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - 1936 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - 1937 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - 1938 (Box-folder 1:13-14)
  - 1939 (Box-folder 1:15-16)
  - 1940 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - 1941 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - 1942-1947 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - 1950 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - 1951 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - 1953 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - 1955-1960 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 1961-1965 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - 1966 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - 1967 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 1968 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - 1969 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - 1970 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - 1971 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 2:9)
  - General correspondence, undated (Box-folder 2:10-11)
  - Condolences, 1972 (Box-folder 3:1-2)
- Writings, 1956
  Contains drafts of Princess Stephanie's memoirs and a 1956 essay on Hungarian politics.
  - Memoir, drafts, undated (Box-folder 3:3)
  - “Anniversary of Disaster," 1956 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Subject Files, 1938-1973
  Contains correspondence, articles, manuscripts, legal documents, and memoranda. Arranged by subject.
  - Court records, 1938-1939 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Biography drafts, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Literary career file, 1965-1972
    - Springer, Axel and Der Stern magazine, 1940-1972 (Box-folder 4:1-4)
    - Pearson, Drew, Anderson, Jack, and "Washington Merry-Go-Round," Column, 1941-1972 (Box-folder 5:1)
    - McHugh, Ryan and Copley News Service, 1972 (Box-folder 5:2)
- Printed Materials, 1929-1972
  Contains printed matter, especially copies of news-clippings from Princess Stephanie's November 1938 trial. Arranged by format.
  - Les Très Riches de Jean de France, Duc de Berry,print, 1970 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - News-clippings, 1929-1938 (Box-folder 6:1-9)
  - News-clippings, 1939-1972 (Box-folder 7:1-12)
- Oversized Material, 1929-1973
  Contains oversized articles, magazines, and news-clippings concerning Princess Stephanie's activities, interests, and associates. The bulk of the content consists of the original news-clippings regarding Princess Stephanie's case against Lord Rothmere in November 1938. Arranged by format.
  - Trial news, November 1939 (Box 8)
  - Printed matter, 1929-1974 (Box 9)